I'm on a mission to change the way that
you think about trading. And when I say
that, I don't mean any kind of woo woo,
envision your dream life and now
manifest a Lambo type of [__] I'm
talking about something much more
important, which is perspective. And
here's why. When you look at all the
problems that most traders go through,
the type that stop you from ever
succeeding at this, when you drill down
to try and find the root cause behind
them, a lot of them tend to relate to
the exact same problem. having the wrong
perspective about what trading is all
about and therefore what you need to
focus on if you want to succeed and
usually this means that traders are
doing the wrong things. So if I can help
you shift your perspective, everything
else should change as well. You'll start
focusing on the right things, developing
the right skills, skills that most
traders don't even realize that they
need. And finally, get yourself on a
path that could actually give you a
chance for succeeding at this. And that
means leaving behind all of the [__]
you see throughout the industry that
just holds people back and instead
focusing on building the skills that
matter. And all of this connects with
what we discussed in the last video. I
told you then that these videos were
connected. And in that video I explained
that there are three mental shifts that
can change the way that you think about
trading. And the first one was what we
discussed in that last video, the idea
of implicit statements. Now if you
haven't seen it, then I recommend going
and watching that video so you can
understand it fully. I'll put a link in
the corner up there or in the
description down below. But let me just
give you a quick recap so that we're on
the same page here. So the idea of
implicit statements is basically when
you make a decision or take an action in
the markets, you're making a statement.
Whether you realize it or not, you are
making a statement through that action.
But the problem is if someone came along
who knows nothing about your trading and
explained to you objectively what
statement your action is making, most
traders wouldn't agree with it. it
wouldn't match what they believe to be
true or what their intention was. But in
the markets, your actions speak louder
than your intentions. The market doesn't
care what you intended to do, what
you're meaning to do. It's just what you
actually do. So if you're meaning one
thing, but your actions are stating
another thing. You're going to end up
with unintended consequences. And in
trading, unintended consequences usually
means that you're depending a lot more
on luck than you should be and a lot
less on skill. That concept of implicit
statements connects directly to the next
two mental shifts that we're going to be
talking about today. And those are
probabilistic thinking and forecasting
the markets. Now, before you click away
thinking, "Yeah, yeah, I already know
trading is about probabilities." And
obviously, we're forecasting the
markets, hold on, because what I'm going
to explain to you in this video is
probably not what you expect. Because
even among traders who understand and
accept that trading is about
probabilities, I still see the same
problem that they only apply that idea,
that way of thinking selectively in
certain parts of their trading and miss
out of other huge parts where it should
apply. And that completely changes their
results, their progress, their
performance. And the same goes for
forecasting as well. I definitely think
that's one area that traders don't think
deeply enough about about what that
actually means. if you're forecasting
the markets and the logic behind that,
what you should therefore be doing. But
the good thing is these two concepts are
directly connected. So once you
understand one of them in a different
way, hopefully in the right way, it also
changes the way you think about the
other. And so you start making
improvements on both sides and that's
when things really start to shift with
your trading. So I will explain all of
this step by step throughout this
session. And I can already tell you it's
probably going to be a long one, but
please stick with it even if you watch
it in more than one sitting because I'm
certain that you'll come away with at
least one big shift in how you see
trading. And as I've said in previous
videos, some of this goes against the
conventional thinking that you see
throughout the industry, but rather than
just disregarding it because it's
different to what you've heard before
and maybe sounds a bit complex in
places, just try your best to follow the
logic. Re-watch it again if you have to.
ask questions in the comments, but try
to understand it fully. Now, just
quickly before we get started, if you
look in the description box, you'll see
a link there to sign up for my free
newsletter. That's where I send more of
my insights and lessons from over 20
years in the markets, including
breakdowns of some of my trades. Just
the other week, I sent a 1-hour video
breaking down all of my trades from the
previous month, including the analysis,
the entries, the decision-m, all of it.
And it's completely free. So, even if
you've got no intention of learning from
me, you think I'm an [__] but you're
just curious about what I send, you
might as well sign up. There's no cost,
and chances are you'll pick up something
useful from it. But anyway, let's get
started. So, I think the best way to
begin is by quickly recapping something
we covered in the last video because
this is the foundation of everything we
do in trading. And so, it directly
connects to the concepts we're talking
about today. And this is the most
important statement that we make as
traders. at the point when we're opening
a trade, what statement are we actually
making when we call something an
opportunity? So, if you look on the left
hand side of the screen, I've mapped two
potential outcomes here, outcome A and
outcome B. And this is just a random
chart. I haven't picked it for any
specific reason. And for simplicity,
I've defined the outcomes as being based
on the swing high and swing low, but
don't read too much into that. It's just
to illustrate the point. So we can think
of these as being the first order
outcomes, the immediate things that
could happen next. And in this example,
outcome A is 30 pips and outcome B is 10
pips. Now imagine we picked this entry
completely at random. We set a timer,
waited for it to go off, and then
flipped a coin to decide whether to go
long or short. So we have absolutely no
advantage. So if we take that trade with
no edge, no advantage, what can we
expect the probabilities to be of
outcome A or outcome B happening? Well,
in this case, the probability of outcome
A is 25% and the probability of outcome
B is 75%. So another way to think about
this is by looking at the trade
expectancy calculation at the bottom of
the screen. So a trade expectancy
calculation is basically telling you if
you took this type of trade again and
again and again on average what return
can you expect per trade. Okay. So if we
take those numbers that we've just
discussed and put it into that
calculation we'll see that the expected
value comes out as zero. In other words
there's no advantage. On average you
would expect no return. So at Duomo we
call these probabilities when there's no
advantage the base rate. So if we're
entering a trade, we're obviously not
doing that if we think we have no
advantage. So in that case, what
statements are we making if we do enter
a trade? Well, if we're going short,
we're basically saying the probability
of outcome B is higher than 75% and
outcome A is lower than 25%. That's what
would make it a positive expectancy
trade. So, if you took those numbers,
put it in the expectancy calculation,
you're going to get a positive number,
meaning on average, you're going to make
a profit from those trades. And on the
other hand, if we're going long, we're
saying the opposite. We're making the
statement that outcome A has a greater
probability than 25% and outcome B has
lower probability than 75%. Hopefully,
everything I've explained makes sense to
you. I think it's quite straightforward,
but maybe watch it again if it's not
clicking for you right away. And if
you've watched my videos before, you're
probably bored of me explaining this,
but it's so important. I want to make
sure it's drilled into every trader. But
what we've looked at up until now is
just an individual opportunity. Now, I
want us to take it a step further and
think about what this means for
longerterm performance. And now, I'm
going to say something that I already
know is going to sound very harsh, but
it's also absolutely true, and the
statistics back it up. So if you think
about all the traders around the world,
almost all of them when they click that
button to enter a trade are doing so
because they think they have some sort
of advantage. Otherwise, why would they
enter the trade? They think they're
predicting something. Now, obviously,
there are also out andout gamblers who
don't think they have an edge and just
want the thrill of opening a trade, but
those aren't really traders. And
likewise, when most of these traders are
spending their time doing their
analysis, they'll do that because they
think they're picking up on meaningful
information. They think they're
detecting important things that have an
impact on the market and have some sort
of predictive power. Otherwise, why
would they spend their time doing it?
But the unfortunate thing is that for
most traders, all of that is a complete
waste of time. They are not analyzing
anything meaningful. It's not important.
It's just noise. There's no predictive
power. They're just falling for
clustering illusions and false
causality. They're not predicting
anything with it. Which means the trades
that they think they're entering with an
advantage are actually no better than
just flipping a coin and choosing heads
or tails, long or short. It's all based
on luck. They think they have an edge,
but really they're just trading the base
rates under this facade of doing
something structured. And if your
probabilities on average are just the
base rates, your expectancy is zero.
Which leads to the big question. How
would that impact your long-term
performance? So, if you're opening
trades with no advantage, an expected
value of zero, you can't expect to do
well over the long run. Your performance
is entirely based on luck. You'll get
some profitable streaks, but it's sort
of like using a civ for a sauce pan.
Your profits just won't stay for long.
they'll be wiped out by losing streaks
and overall the long-term return will
average out being zero. And the only way
you make money in that situation is if
you happen to stop trading right in the
middle of a good lucky run, cash out,
and walk away forever, go and retire on
a beach somewhere. But obviously, that's
not a great plan for your trading
career. And I'm sure if you're watching
videos about trading, you're not
intending to just go on a lucky streak
and then give up. Now, these charts that
you see on screen are just to
demonstrate the point. I'm not
suggesting that every trader in that
lefth hand chart converges to a return
of zero at exactly the same point. But
what I want you to get from this chart
is that yes, there'll be profitable
streaks and losing streaks, ups and
downs, but there'll be no positive
long-term performance. Nothing
dependable that you can actually rely
on. So then what's the point of doing
it? And most traders who are making
profits right now are simply on the
upwards part of this cycle without
realizing it. they think they've tapped
into something that's working when the
reality is they're just on a lucky
streak. But you might think, well,
what's the problem with that? If there's
no advantage or disadvantage, you'll
just be at break even. Like, doesn't
matter that much. But that's also not
the case because with every trade we
open, we also pay a transaction cost.
Things like the spread, commission,
swaps. So imagine without transaction
costs, maybe you have one trade that
makes a profit of 1% and then the next
trade loses 1%. So you're back at break
even, but when you factor in the
transaction costs, the profits are
obviously a bit lower and the losses are
going to be a bit bigger. So with the
same trades, you're going to be below
break even. And when that plays out over
the long run, what originally would have
had you averaging a return of zero is
now putting you into an ever growing
loss. And this is the real reason that
most traders lose. When you look at the
industry statistics, whether you believe
it's 95% of traders losing or a bit less
than that, 90, 85, whatever, it's not
that all of those traders are taking
negative expectancy trades, is that they
have no edge either way. They're trading
based on the base rates. It's like
flipping a coin, but they're losing
because of the accumulation of
transaction costs. And you know, I see
some really terrible advice throughout
the trading industry. But one that I've
seen coming up time and time again is
people suggesting that you can just keep
trading, keep collecting that data, and
if you're profitable, great. Now you've
got a profitable strategy. You just keep
doing that. And if you lose, now you
know you can start doing the opposite,
and you'll have a profitable strategy
instead. But this is complete [__]
nonsense. If you have an average
expectancy of zero and you're losing in
real money due to transaction costs,
guess what happens when you start doing
the opposite when you start trading the
opposite way? Well, the outcome will be
exactly the [__] same. Listen, I just
wanted to come back and quickly add
something here that obviously a lot of
the traders that lose are doing so
because they're risking too much money,
being overleveraged, or holding on to
losing trades way beyond the point they
should have exited them because they're
hoping it eventually comes back to being
profitable, but then it never does. So,
those traders never get to the point
where they see their probabilities
playing out. But those aren't really the
trades I'm talking about. Instead, I'm
talking about the traders who feel like
they're doing things the right way with
appropriate risk management and all
things like that, but still don't
succeed. Now, I know that it can be
difficult to accept that this may also
be the case for you if you're currently
losing with your trading because
everyone is so persuaded that their
analysis and their strategies are
meaningful and the problem is something
else. Because it's really hard to accept
that something you've been learning,
something you've been spending time
doing is contributing nothing more than
a coin flip would. But don't worry, I
also have some good news for you because
making money from your trading in a
dependable way over the long term is
actually simpler than you think. Well,
it's also a bit more complex than you
think as well. But the first part is
simple at least. It basically comes down
to this. Your average positive
expectancy, in other words, the
advantage that you have over the base
rate on average with your trades, just
needs to be higher than the average
transaction costs. So here's a simple
example just to illustrate that point.
I'm not saying it's exactly like this,
but I just want you to understand the
logic. So let's say that your average
transaction cost is one pip, but your
average trade expectancy is 5 pips. Then
congratulations, you're going to be
making money overall, assuming all else
is equal, like position sizes on the
trades and that kind of thing. But
obviously, this is only going to be the
case if that's genuinely the level of
positive expectancy. because it's one
thing for me to decide a trade is
positive expectancy, but that doesn't
mean it actually is. And so we can think
of this with different numbers as well.
Let's say that your average edge, so
your average expectancy is just one pip,
right? So you're still technically a
profitable trader, but if your
transaction costs are also on average
one pip, you'll be breaking even. Now,
once again, this is all massively
oversimplified. Real trading is much
messier than this and the numbers won't
be so straightforward, but I'm pointing
this out to you so that hopefully you
just get the idea because imagine your
average expectancy is zero because
you're trading the base rates and
average transaction costs are one pip.
After a,000 trades, you've just paid out
a,000 pips. That's significant. But I
want you to notice that here we're
talking about averages. Because here's
the thing, not all of your trades need
to have an advantage. Of course, you
wouldn't open them if you didn't think
they did, but just because you think
there's an edge doesn't mean there
actually is. So, it's inevitable for
every trader that some trades that you
take won't be positive expectancy. So,
imagine only a quarter of your trades
actually have positive expectancy and
the rest we can assume on average have
an expectancy of zero, no edge. Now,
it's important to understand here that
this doesn't mean all the positive
expectancy trades result in a profit and
it doesn't mean all of the ones with no
edge result in a loss. Both types will
have both profits and losses. But
overall, the ones with positive
expectancy will make a profit over the
long run over a larger sample size and
the ones with no advantage won't, at
least not in a dependable way over the
long run, something that you can rely
on. So if we imagine the trades with no
advantage more or less balancing each
other out over time, so you don't make
anything, you don't lose anything, then
all you're paying out is the transaction
costs. So therefore, you can still make
money from your trading as long as the
ones with genuine positive expectancy
make enough for profit to exceed the
transaction costs on all of the trades.
So if you take a look at the chart on
the right hand side, I've put this here
to try and help demonstrate the point.
It's obviously not entirely realistic
because well, a few reasons, but one of
them being that it suggests all the
trades are happening at once and that
there's the same number of those trades
and so on and so on. But it's just to
help you think it through and I want you
to think of it this way. The red line is
from the trades where you have no
advantage. So sometimes it's a profit,
sometimes it's a loss, but overall it's
drifting downwards because of the
accumulation of those transaction costs.
So it's a deepening loss. The green line
on the other hand are the ones with
positive expectancy. Again, some of them
will be losses, some of them will be
profits, but overall because it's
positive expectancy, it's going upwards.
And when you take them both together,
what you end up with is the yellow line,
which is the overall P&L with all of the
trades combined. And once again, this is
not an accurate depiction. It's not
intended to be completely accurate, like
this is what it looks like. I'm just
putting this here to help get the point
across. I do still know that I'll
probably get destroyed in the comment
section because why the [__] not? That's
what people do. But anyway, hopefully
that helps you get the point. So, let's
stick with this example where only a
quarter of your trades genuinely have
positive expectancy. So, if that's the
case, how can you improve your
profitability? Well, there are two broad
ways that you can do that. The first is
to obviously increase the number of
trades that do genuinely have positive
expectancy. Therefore, trading more
based on skill and reducing the amount
of luck involved. All right, just
another thing I quickly want to add here
because it's important. I'm not saying
that you'll know which of your trades
actually does have positive expectancy
or not. Because obviously, if that was
the case, you wouldn't take the trades
that don't. You only really find out
your accuracy levels by going through a
calibration process, which is something
I explained in a previous video, and
I'll chuck it up there in the corner, so
you can go and watch that if you want
to. And the second way is to increase
the size of the advantage in the
positive expectancy traits. So how far
from base rate the estimated probability
is. Now I can already sense the
complaints about that second one coming
my way because how can you increase the
advantage when you don't control the
markets. The probabilities of a
situation are the probabilities. You
can't increase them unless you're just
fooling yourself. But that's not going
to improve your profitability. And all
of that is true, but it's also not what
I'm suggesting. You do it by increasing
the threshold for what you count as an
opportunity. If you'd previously look at
something that has a positive expectancy
above 0.2R and count that as an
opportunity, you might now change your
threshold to only take trades when the
positive expectancy is over 0.5R. In
doing so, the trades that genuinely have
positive expectancy will have a bigger
advantage, and the ones that are just
the base rates end up being more or less
the same anyway. Now, regardless of
which of these ways you're aiming to
improve your profitability, it's going
to come down to the exact same things.
So, when you improve one, you improve
both of them. And those things are doing
better analysis and being more accurate
with your probability estimates. And for
a lot of you, that's going to mean
actually going through probability
estimates in the first place. And yes,
it is possible to get more accurate with
your probability estimates. I've shown
this in previous videos. I won't be
going into it in detail today, but it is
a recurring topic on this channel. So,
if you don't want to miss any future
lessons, make sure you subscribe and
switch on notifications or sign up for
the newsletter and then you'll get all
other training videos as well that will
walk you through this. All right. Now,
before anyone says anything, no, I'm not
doing an outfit change for each
different segment. Like, I think I'm
[__] Taylor Swift or something. I've
just had to come back to film the rest
of this video on a different day. So,
there's your explanation. So what we've
covered so far is all about
probabilistic thinking. I think most
traders accept that trading is about
probabilities, but usually only to the
extent that they accept that each trade
could result in a loss. But hopefully
you can see now that it goes much
further than that. And it should be a
much bigger focus in everything you're
doing. And there are also many other
ways that probabilities impact other
areas of your trading. Things that most
traders completely ignore. And these can
completely change your performance or
the decisions that you make that impact
both your individual trades and your
entire trading career. But we will go
deeper on all of that in the coming
videos. I've got a lot of things
planned. But for now, I want us to
expand on what we've been discussing so
far and look at how that impacts the way
that we analyze the markets and find
trades. So let's think back to that
example that I gave you earlier when we
talked about what makes an opportunity.
We had two potential outcomes and we
were talking about the probabilities of
each of them. So when you have a range
of potential outcomes and you estimate
the probabilities of those outcomes,
what you have is a forecast. Even if you
just conclude that the probabilities are
the base rates and that there's no
advantage, that is still a forecast.
Therefore, a trade opportunity isn't
necessarily a setup or when the market
matches your entry criteria or any of
the other things that you've been told
to look for. A trade opportunity is
simply a forecast that you estimate has
positive expectancy. And so, this leads
us to an important conclusion. If a
trade opportunity is just a forecast
that you think has positive expectancy,
that means technically you could be
forecasting in the markets continuously
and just take trades when you see that
there's positive expectancy. Now, in
reality, it doesn't make sense to
constantly forecast the markets because
like what are you going to do? Update
your estimates every single time the
price ticks up or down? It'll be [__]
insane. So instead we look to forecast
when each potential outcome completes
and we've got new potential outcomes or
when certain things take place in the
markets that gives us new meaningful
information so that we can update our
forecast in a material way. So not every
single price tick but when there's
something more substantial. So take the
example on screen. It might be the case
that each of the markers that you can
see were moments where we could complete
a forecast or update a forecast. The
ones in red had no advantage, meaning we
estimated that they were either at the
base rate or below the expectancy
threshold, like we discussed a moment
ago, the threshold for taking an
opportunity. Whereas the green ones were
positive expectancy above the threshold
and could be taken as trades. And this
is exactly what we do with the Duomo
method. Yes, we still use setups for
timing and entry. And that's for two
reasons. Firstly because it's a tipping
point for the probabilities as it's the
moment that we expect a shift in
activity to happen and secondly because
of what I explained in the last video
that it's an optimal point for
expectancy but the opportunity itself
doesn't come from a setup. The
opportunity comes from the forecast and
that's derived from something else. But
the problem is that most traders don't
put themselves in a position to even be
able to do this. And let me give you a
simple analogy to explain why. Think
about weather forecasting. So throughout
history, people looked up at the sky or
the world around them for different cues
that would help them to predict what
weather is coming their way. And this is
known as weather wisdom. You might have
heard of famous sayings like red sky at
night, sailor's delight or shepherd's
delight or as a kid I thought it was
angel delight. That's weather wisdom,
right? assigning context to observed
patterns and then looking for those same
patterns again in the future and
assuming the same context. And actually,
some studies show that there is a
certain level of accuracy to these
forecasts because they reflect real
atmospheric patterns. But they're also
too simplistic and too context dependent
to be consistently relied upon. In some
situations, they'll be amazingly
accurate, but in others, they'll come to
the completely wrong conclusion. So
imagine that you had a weather app and
it was all just based on weather wisdom.
How much would you trust in what it
shows you? On the other hand, when we
look at what weather forecasting is like
these days, weather forecasters rely on
a huge amount of very accurate data
points which they then run through
complex computer systems to produce
these incredibly accurate probabilities
that you see in the weather apps like
the chance of rain and things like that.
They don't assign meaning to predefined
patterns. They look at each situation
uniquely and try to understand the
specific context of that moment. And
this is exactly what you see in trading
as well. Most traders rely on a
predefined set of factors that they've
already given meaning to. These are
based on previous observations that
they've made or just what's been passed
on to them by another trader or whoever
it is that they're learning from. Then
they analyze the markets looking for
those specific factors. And when they do
come up, maybe in a particular order or
a sequence, they'll assign a predefined
context to them. They've already assumed
the meaning. So they're focused on a
small amount of information and have
already decided ahead of time what that
small amount of information will mean
and what it will mean for the next price
movements. They've already assumed the
context for those situations.
But if we already know how important
probabilities are for profitable
trading, we need to be as accurate as we
can in how we estimate them. This can't
be done by just packaging up the market
into these neat little boxes that we
assign some meaning to. The markets are
dynamic and each situation that we see
is unique. Now, of course, there will be
many similarities, but there will also
be many differences as well, and those
differences matter just as much as the
things that are similar. So the only way
that we can increase the accuracy of our
forecasts is by analyzing and
interpreting all meaningful information
and coming to a unique conclusion about
the context at that moment in time. But
that's just not possible with how most
traders approach the markets. And that's
exactly why they end up taking trades
where they think they have an edge but
actually have no edge at all. Now I do
realize that all of this might sound a
bit abstract at this point. So, I want
to start getting into some of the
specifics so you can fully understand
what I'm explaining to you here. So,
let's start off by thinking about what
most traders do. And you might even be
doing this yourself, especially if
you're following some sort of strategy.
So, there'll usually be a sequence of
things that you look for. In this case,
it might be that X is looking at a
higher time frame to see if there's a
particular type of trend or structure
that tells you something about the
market. When you see that particular
trend or that structure, then why might
be waiting for a particular cue on a
lower time frame that tells you
something else. There are all kinds of
popular ones these days like fair value
gaps or liquidity sweeps. And then zed
might be the price returning into a
certain area. And this final step tells
you that the market is ready to sell off
or to shoot up. So you enter a short
trade or a long trade or whatever it
might be and away you go. Obviously,
those elements are just an example and
quite vague examples because I don't
want to take something that's real and
throw someone under the bus by using
them as my example of what's being done
badly. But you can think about your own
trading and just swap any of those
predefined things that I've mentioned
for any other predefined thing that
you're using or that you see any other
traders using. And it doesn't have to be
three steps like this. It could be any
number of steps in the sequence, but
essentially it all means the same. It
means that you're already deciding the
meaning this combination of different
things gives you without taking into
account all the unique aspects of that
situation. You're saying because X, Y,
and then zed happened, it means the
market is doing this, so the price is
likely to do that next. But that means
you're not really assessing all the
factors that make up that unique
situation. And as a result, your
probabilities are very unlikely to be
correct. And in fact, most traders don't
use probabilities. They rely on success
rates. Meaning, they do their back
testing and see how many times that
particular situation was profitable in
the past and then assume that that's the
rate it will be profitable in the
future. But success rate is not the same
as probability. Now, I've used this
analogy many times before. I'm a
creature of habit. I'm going to use it
again. But let's say I wanted to know
what is the chance of it raining today.
Now I can look back on previous data and
I can see that it rained in London over
140 days last year. And yes, that's
true. That's quite depressing. So that's
like let's say around 40% of the time.
So I can say there's a 40% chance of
rain state. Now that's the equivalent of
what traders are doing when they use
success rates. But hopefully in this
context, you can see how it's completely
[__] ridiculous. What if it's a clear
sky state? What if there are dark clouds
over? What if it's mid July? What if
it's midFebruary? It's obvious that it's
not going to be a 40% chance every day.
The context matters. And for your
trades, there are also all sorts of
differences that change the context. Not
to mention the fact that the sizes of
the potential outcomes will be different
each time. And listen, obviously, I
completely understand the desire to keep
things simple with your trading. But the
problem is a lot of the people in this
industry who tell you that you only need
to keep trading simple and teach you
these simple approaches are just
following simple marketing tactics. Make
something sound effortless, easy, and
quick and you'll get lots of people on
board. [__] it. It pretty much does it
itself. It's turnkey. But remember, our
job as traders is to forecast the global
financial markets. If you're just
spotting, plotting, and labeling things,
and then assigning some predefined
context that some over-the-top flashy
[__] on Instagram has given you, do you
really think that's enough? Do you
really think that's a skill that 95% of
traders fail at? Or do you think that
maybe most of those traders fail because
forecasting the global financial markets
involves more skill than that? Of
course, it's easy to blame trading
psychology for people losing. is easy to
blame people not using good risk
management. But the simple fact is that
most of the time is that you just don't
have an edge. Most trading psychology
problems exist when you don't rely on
the correct skills and they go away when
you do. Now don't get me wrong at Duomo
we do also look at structure and we do
also apply simple logic to certain
situations like we might look at a
higher time frame for a particular shift
in structure and know that that's now
the trigger to go and analyze deeper to
understand what's going on but those are
more like cues to go deeper. The real
analysis is always done by breaking down
the specifics of that situation and
understanding what it's really showing
you. So how do you start making these
improvements in your trading approach?
Well, first you need to understand what
information is important. And these are
the core foundations that I think most
traders tend to miss. So this diagram
here is what I call the market context
hierarchy. And don't worry, I'll explain
each of the segments to you in more
detail. But if we look right at the
bottom, there's the raw input. It's the
main information we get about what's
happening in the markets. And that is
transactions. And we can also put
potential transactions in this category
as well if we include the order book. So
when a trade happens, what information
exists? We know the price the
transaction happened at, the quantity,
the time, and often what side of the
book it was executed on. Now that's a
very small amount of information. Can I
understand what's happening in the
market from any individual transaction?
Maybe very occasionally, but not
usually. But groups of transactions
together give us an entirely new
meaning. And I refer to these groups as
activity. And there are all kinds of
variations of activity. But as you'll
see in a moment, there are still only a
limited number of things that we can
read from activity. So there are more
possibilities and variations than the
individual transactions. And we can get
more meaning from that, but it's still
not enough to fully understand a
situation. But groups of activity
together give us the market context. And
here there are pretty much infinite
variations. Every single different group
of activity gives us a unique market
context. And it's by understanding that
that context for that specific situation
that we can create a reliable forecast.
And remember a trade opportunity is just
a forecast that we estimate has positive
expectancy. So a simple way to think of
all of this is that transactions are
like individual words. They say
something, but you can't really
understand much of them on their own.
But a group of words together can form a
sentence and that carries more meaning.
And when you have groups of sentences
together, you can fully understand the
context of something, whether that's a
paragraph or a whole novel. But what
most traders are doing is packaging up
certain types of activity and saying,
"Here, this is the context every single
time that these happen." It's like when
I was a kid going on holiday, memorizing
things from a phrase book when I was on
the plane, thinking that when I land,
I'll be able to talk to people in that
language. Like even if I hear the phrase
that I think I recognize, it doesn't
mean that it's in the right context.
Just think about when your girlfriend
tells you, "Don't worry about it." That
might mean that you can chill out and
genuinely not worry about it. Or it
might mean you're in a doghouse. And
trust me, you're asking for trouble if
you don't get the context right when she
says that. So, let me explain each of
these segments to you. I'm just going to
do a quick run through so that you can
understand the basics, but I can always
do a follow-up video for each of them to
explain things in detail at a later
point in time. But for now, we'll just
do a quick once over. First, we have
transactions. It's really important that
you understand how trades happen and
what causes prices to move. Hopefully,
you know this already, but if you don't,
you're not alone. It seems most traders
have never learned this, which is really
surprising. So, I'll give you the very
simple version for now, just so you
broadly get what's going on. and then
we'll go into more detail in a separate
video. So, we can think of there being
two broad types of orders in the
markets. There are limit orders and
market orders. Limit orders come under
different names. You often hear them
referred to as resting orders or a whole
bunch of other specific types. But
basically, a limit order is where a
trader is saying, I'll transact this
quantity at this specific price or
better. So, if the market doesn't reach
that price, their order won't be filled.
And if it does, great. they'll maybe get
their order filled. On the other hand, a
market order is where a trader says, "I
want to transact right now with this
quantity right now at whatever price I
can get." And this is the type that
retail traders usually use the most. So,
we can think of limit orders as being
the more patient, more passive type,
whereas market orders have more urgency
and are more aggressive. They just want
to get filled right now. Now, limit
orders will appear in the order book.
You'll see these in the depth of market,
things like that. And you can think of
the order book sort of like advertising.
So these traders are saying, "Hey, look,
I've got this quantity to transact at
this price." It's like advertising the
the trade. And they'll either be on the
right hand side of the book, meaning
that the orders are looking to sell or
the left hand side where they're looking
to buy. So these limit orders are the
liquidity in the market. And this
liquidity is then taken by the market
orders. So if I have a market order to
buy in the market, I'll transact against
the limit orders liquidity on the right
hand side of the order book. Whereas if
I have a market order to sell, I'll be
transacting against the orders on the
left hand side. And this relationship is
what leads to prices moving in the
markets. So let me give you a simple
example. Let's say that I'm executing
this market order to buy 120 lots of a
particular asset. So I now need
liquidity to transact against at the
price 1.356.
There are 50 lots available. So I'll
transact against those. And so the price
is at 1.356.
But I still have 70 lots left to
transact. So I need more liquidity. So
now price moves up to 1.357. And I take
the 60 lots available there. But my
market order still has 10 left to
transact. So price moves up again to
1.358 and I take 10 of the 40 there. So
price has moved up as I found the
liquidity to transact my market order.
So this means prices move based on
imbalances between volume, the market
orders and liquidity, the limit orders.
The bigger the imbalance, the more price
will move. The lower the imbalance, the
less it will move. And if it's balanced,
it won't need to move at all because
there's enough liquidity at the current
prices to transact against. Now, that's
a really overly simplified version. It's
a bit more complex than that in reality.
There are many other things going on. I
mean, markets are usually a continuous
double auction process. So, there are
these transactions happening on both
sides. But just like I mentioned before,
I'll explain all of it in much more
detail in a separate video. For now, I
just want you to understand that when
we're talking about transactions, it's
this process that's happening. And this
is some of the information that you look
at when you're doing orderflow analysis,
which is something that we use to
support what we're doing with the Duo
method. So, it's like a an extra way of
us analyzing deeper in the markets. But
the thing is, you can't understand the
full context just by looking at
transactions alone. So, let's move on to
the next segment, activity, which is
what we get from groups of transactions.
So, the levels of balance or imbalance
at different points in the market, where
those change and where they're likely to
change in the future gives us a lot of
information about what's really going
on. And these are basically the
movements that we can see happening
visually on the chart. And I think of
them as contextual factors, but when you
really think about it, there are only
really a limited number of things we can
actually pick up on. We can see where
turning points happen, where
consolidation happens, how much momentum
there is behind a move, the size of a
move, the depth of pullbacks within a
move or within a trend, the level of
volume, and if you're using the depth of
market or other similar tools like
bookmap and things like that, you can
see the orders or liquidity. There
really isn't anything else we can see in
the market. Everything is just derived
from some combination of those factors.
But there are endless variations that we
could see in each of these individual
contextual factors. And those variations
give us a lot of information because
they're telling us something about the
balance or imbalance, who's in control
in the market, and where there have been
shifts in activity, which is all useful
information for understanding the full
context of the situation. So, for
example, when we're looking at turning
points, reversals in the market, we have
where the turning point happens, how
quickly it takes place, how strong the
move away from it is. We have different
levels of momentum. Like, think about
how quickly the price moves from point A
to point B. That's telling us something
about the composition of that move, the
level of imbalance that's causing it.
What about depth of pullbacks? What's it
telling us if it's just a small
fluctuation compared to actual waves?
What if there are no pullbacks at all?
Then we've got the size of the move. Why
were there bearish moves like this at
this point and then this one was much
longer? What changed? Why did it change?
Or with consolidation, where does that
consolidation happen? How tight was the
consolidation? How long did it last?
Every single time that we look at the
markets, there's a different unique
variation of these different contextual
factors. And together they give us the
narrative of what's been happening so
far and allow us to interpret the
current situation to paint a picture of
what's been happening and what may
happen next. And by the way, all of
these that we've just been through will
allow you to understand what's happened
in the past. But to be able to
anticipate what may happen next to plan
the potential outcomes and therefore to
be able to trade well, you need to be
able to anticipate where future shifts
in activity will take place. And to do
this effectively, you need an underlying
market theory like the Duo market theory
that we use because you need to
anticipate why price might shift at a
specific point. Like why that point and
not five pips before or 10 pips after
what is it that makes that specific
price point the place where the activity
is going to shift? And that includes
something that I call invisible levels,
which is anticipating where shifts in
activity may happen at price points
where the market has never been before.
Because imagine that you're in a long
trade and the market's reaching record
highs, like if you've been long gold
recently. How do you know where the end
of that potential outcome is going to
be? If you're just going to be reacting
based on emerging price activity, you're
likely to end up trading base rates. And
listen, this is definitely something
that we'll discuss in more detail in a
separate video because there are so many
implicit statements related to this that
traders just don't realize that they're
making with their trades. And because of
that, they end up relying a lot more on
luck with their trades than they
realize. And you're probably noticing I
have a lot of videos planned. I've said
this will be in a different video about
three or four times in this, but that's
because I've got a lot of videos on the
way. So stay tuned. Subscribe to the
channel if you haven't because they'll
be coming thick and fast. But here's the
thing I want you to understand. Rather
than using the equivalent of weather
wisdom and having a set of things that
you look for with a predefined context,
which will usually be wrong, we can use
these activity types, the contextual
factors to understand what's uniquely
going on in that situation, just like
reading a book. In other words, when
you're following a market and seeing the
price movements developing, you can pick
up on the information that that gives
you and use it to update what you
understand about that market. So here's
just a basic example only looking at
price structure. And by doing this, it
was actually possible to anticipate
potential key turning points even before
adding any levels to the chart or
anything like that because that would
all come after this. It's by
understanding the underlying context
first that you will know what type of
levels will build on that context to
show you the information that you need
rather than just adding levels
arbitrarily just cuz they can be added.
And by the way, I do have to point out
that what you see in this screenshot is
complete overkill. I've only done this
to demonstrate the point about how much
information there is even just from the
structure characteristics. I'm not
saying you have to cover your chart in
information like this, but this is just
the basics related to structure
characteristics that you see in this
screenshot. And I actually did all of
this on a live stream with members of
our community. It took about 4 hours, so
it was a long session. And so from that
previous information, I can then start
explaining the context at certain points
in time or identifying interesting
points where there was an interesting
shift in activity where I feel that I
need to investigate further to
understand what's been going on, what
caused it, why that point. I can then
add relevant levels and by doing this I
can fully understand the cause effect
sequence that takes place in the market.
As a result of that, I can then
anticipate the next potential outcomes
and make very precise judgments about
the probabilities of them happening.
Now, look, I'm just going to say it
again, but don't get too caught up with
the text that you see on that chart.
It's just some basics to give you an
example. I don't want you to take that
and think, okay, that's what I've got to
do. Like, that's sort of focusing on the
superficial aspects rather than
understanding the logic of what I'm
explaining to you here. And there are
much more nuance things we could add to
that chart. You could of course add key
significant levels that explain the
shifts in activity and could be used to
anticipate future shifts in activity.
But all of this is just a basic example
is the premise rather than what you're
actually seeing there. Because really
what I want to get across to you is that
there is so much information that we can
get from each situation in the markets
that will inform us about the
probabilities of what may happen next.
And if you don't pay attention to this
information and just try to keep things
simple by looking for a sequence of
predefined cues and treating them the
same way each time, you might be making
things easier for yourself, but you'll
also be making it far less likely that
you'll actually have any kind of edge.
And this applies to so many things that
have become really popular over recent
years. Things like head and shoulders
patterns, which have been popular for
decades, liquidity sweeps, wick fills,
even simple things like swing high lows.
Now, I'm not saying that these things
are inherently useless or bad to use. I
mean, at Duomo, we use swing high lows
along with other types of levels and
zones. The important thing is that you
don't preassign some specific meaning to
them and that you understand what it is
that they're actually showing you or
what they are meant to be showing you
and whether there's something better
that could show you that in a more
precise way by thinking about that
hierarchy of activity. You need to
understand what they mean within the
right context. because let's think about
the implicit statements that are being
made with some of these different
things. Let's think about a head and
shoulders pattern. Now, I didn't want to
throw anyone under the bus by choosing
certain images and singling them out.
So, I just took the first four images
that came up on a Google image search
for this. I haven't chosen these ones
for any particular reason. Okay? So, if
it's your image there, I'm sorry. But
think about what statements are being
made. Firstly, are all of these head and
shoulders patterns the same? Do they
look the same? Can we really treat them
all in exactly the same way? And do all
head and shoulders patterns really tell
us the same thing about the market? What
about the rest of the context? You know,
if we think about what a head and
shoulders pattern is made of? If we
break it down in terms of the activity
types, the contextual factors, can't we
deconstruct it and figure out the actual
context each time rather than a pattern?
Like, think about the activity types we
have here. It's just a series of price
moves and turning points that appear on
the charts in a certain way. But what
about the level of momentum in each of
the price moves? What about how strong
the turning point is? What if it
consolidates in between? What about the
pullbacks within the moves? What about
where the turning points happen? How
strong the turning points and all that
kind of stuff. You see, it's not the
pattern itself that matters. It's those
factors. And by understanding how to
interpret them, you can figure out the
correct context each time. And as a
result, you'll know when a head and
shoulders pattern is more likely to work
or not. Or you don't even need to rely
on the head and shoulders pattern
because it's got nothing to do with the
pattern and everything to do with the
activity types that construct it. And if
we treat the patterns the same each and
every time, we're making the implicit
statement that they all have the same
context, that the variations of the
activity types don't matter, that all
that matters is the pattern itself.
We're saying of all the endless types of
context that we could have, every time
there's a head and shoulders pattern, it
specifically shows this the same exact
context every time. And that is just
wrong. If you really want to understand
what's going on in the markets, you need
to break things down to first principles
as much as you can. Deconstruct things
to their component parts and focus on
interpreting those. So think about what
activity makes up this thing that I'm
looking at. What is it that I'm really
analyzing here? And is it really
reflecting that properly? You know,
quite a few years ago now, I put out a
video explaining why traditional chart
patterns are useless and have no
predictive power. And it's been proven
in many studies. And of course, as you'd
expect, I got a lot of hate comments on
that because people get really tribal
about trading approaches and stuff. But
the funny thing was the argument that
people kept giving to defend chart
patterns. They were saying things like,
"Of course, when you just test patterns,
they're going to give you bad results
because you have to use them in specific
situations after already analyzing the
markets to determine that price is
likely to reverse and then just use the
pattern as the trigger for entering a
trade." Okay. So, in that case, what do
you think is more likely to be having
the predictive power here? Is it this
arbitrary pattern or is it the rest of
the stuff that you've used to interpret
the markets and make up that forecast?
It's like people can't see past the
pattern or the other things they're
using to realize that any success
they're having is coming from the rest
of the work they're doing. Because the
thing is, if you stay in the markets
long enough, even if you're doing the
wrong things, you will develop implicit
knowledge without realizing it. So,
you'll start detecting the activity
shifts that we've been discussing, but
not necessarily knowing that that's what
you're detecting. You just get a feeling
about things. you know, you think it's
this particular thing that you're basing
your opportunity on, the pattern or
whatever it might be, but then you can't
quite explain why there are certain
situations where you decide just to not
trade it. But if you make these things
more explicit by actually developing the
skill of interpreting the context based
on the overall activity, you'll be far
more successful. But unfortunately, it
always seems to be the case in this
industry that people are too afraid of
going against the crowd, thinking for
themselves, questioning the logic, and
questioning whether maybe some of these
things that everyone is going on about
are just false illusions. And it's just
like the one that's become so popular
recently that it's all traders talk
about on social media these days, fair
value gaps. So, here are a few
variations. And I haven't spotted these
for myself. I've actually taken them
from the most popular place that people
learn about these and taken their
screenshots and put them on this. So,
what statement are we making about
these? Are we going to treat all of
these fair value gaps in the same way?
Give them the same level of importance.
Give them the same context. If not, how
are we differentiating? So, think about
the information that traders are taking
from a fair value gap about what's going
on in the market. What is it that
they're interpreting from it? and think,
isn't there a better way to get that
information that avoids having to make
so many assumptions? I mean, the
assumption people make about how fair
value gaps are created in the first
place is basically a description of
something that's called a stacked
imbalance. That's a very basic orderflow
concept. But if you try to identify that
from a price candle, there'll be many
times when there isn't a stacked
imbalance. So, wouldn't it be more
effective to use a footprint chart and
actually find the stacked imbalance and
then instead of making the assumption
that there'll be a rebalancing of a
prior inefficiency and unfilled orders
on the other side of the book that can
transact when price returns to the zone,
why not go to the source and confirm if
that's actually the case rather than
making the assumption based on this
candle formation. I mean, is it possible
that FEGs will appear when they don't
actually represent the underlying logic
they're meant to? Yes, of course. could
sometimes be a coincidence. So instead,
why not go and find the right evidence
for it based on order flow or something
like that? Like, can you see the
difference? In one case, we're assigning
a meaning to a candle formation and
therefore making a whole bunch of
assumptions that could in some
situations be wrong. In other words,
relying on luck in many cases. And in
the other case, we're confirming the
information so that we don't have to
assume anything. Now listen, I don't
want to get into an argument about
whether fair value gaps are meaningful
or not or whether I described it in the
exact way that you understand. I want
you to think about the logic of what I'm
saying here rather than the superficial
stuff. Don't let the point I'm making
get lost in, you know, something that
gets you hotheaded. You know, I think
fair value gaps can be useful in certain
situations, but it's context dependent
and it's just much best to rely on the
source information rather than relying
on a candle formation. So, if you want
to go into the comments just like that
chart pattern video and try to argue
with me about how I'm wrong or tell me
your great results as anecdotal evidence
from a sample size of one, go ahead. But
you will be wasting your time because I
honestly couldn't give a [__] So,
moving swiftly on the root cause problem
for all of these issues that I've
explained and the reason most traders
never develop an edge all comes down to
how traders usually learn. So, think
about what most traders focus on when
they first start learning. They want to
learn the strategies. That's the fun bit
as sexy as what everyone's doing videos
about. But the problem is they haven't
got any knowledge about the markets.
They haven't got any way to filter out
what's logical and what's illogical. So,
how can they choose which strategy to
learn? Well, it's going to be based on
the halo effect. They'll look at which
trading approaches are most popular or
talked about the most online. Like on
social media, everyone is learning the
same exact [__] approach. Or they'll
look at which people teaching certain
methods look most successful or sound
most confident, who has the most
testimonials, or who just has the best
salesperson. And as a result, they end
up wasting their time, money, and effort
learning things that are illogical
without realizing it because they have
no way of being able to differentiate
what is worth their time or not. But
instead, developing a skill or acquiring
knowledge is like a tree. First you
start with the roots and build your
foundation knowledge and once you have
that you'll understand what direction to
go from there. So you can move on to the
trunk which are the core pillars that
make up that particular thing. Then from
there you have the branches which are
specific concepts and theories that
you'll be able to tell are logical
because you understand the core pillars
and the foundations. You can already say
well that theory can't make sense. That
concept's a load of [__] And
because of that, then when you get to
the leaves, which are things like how
you enter trades, strategies, and so on,
then you'll actually have something
that's meaningful because it's based on
theories that are logical, that are
related to the core pillars and the real
foundations. And then there's a final
addition, which is the fruit, which are
the outputs that provide the seeds for
further improvement. But like I said,
the problem for most traders is that
they jump straight to the leaves by
focusing on strategies first. But you
won't know if they're hanging on logical
concepts and theories that relate back
to how the markets actually work or if
they're just based on [__] But if
you build from the bottom up, you build
the right understanding to be able to
instantly filter which trading
approaches or which concepts are
illogical, not worth learning, you can
tell what things are meaningless and are
just analyzing noise. You can start
building your edge by developing the
right skills and start treating this
like a professional job rather than just
a computer game. Because I'll say it
again, if forecasting the global
financial markets was as simple as
playing an adult version of where's
Wally or where's Wildo where you're just
spotting patterns, plotting levels, and
waiting for setups. It would not be
something that most traders lose at.
Developing a reliable edge over the long
term, something you can really depend on
to build a career on, doesn't come from
approaching the markets as a pattern
recognition exercise. It comes from
treating it as a problem-solving
exercise. And if you think that sounds
too complex for you to learn and
therefore you want to go and learn
something simple because you don't think
you're capable, you're wrong. The
industry might have made you believe
that you should keep things simple and
easy because if it's too complex, you're
not really going to get it. But you are
capable of more. Maybe you need to
remind yourself of who the [__] you are
and what you're able to do and then get
to work building real skills rather than
just memorizing setups and strategies
and thinking that will work. So I hope
that by changing the way that you think
about the role of probabilities in
trading, what it actually means to
forecast the markets and find a trade
and the implicit statements that you're
making with all the actions and
decisions that you take with your
trading, you can start on a much better
path. So this knowledge tree that you
see on screen here is just a basic
overview. But if you're serious about
making this work, stick around on this
channel and I'll explain the entire
learning path for you in detail along
with all the logic behind it and why
each bit is important, what role it
plays. But for now, I need to stop
talking.